[siren wailing]
[birds chirping]
‎在封锁边境…
[narrator] Before closing their borders...
‎限制公民出行之前…
and locking down their citizens...
‎许多世界领导人 ‎都对席卷全球的新型病毒轻描淡写
many world leaders downplayed the new virus that was sweeping the globe.
‎局势完全可控
[in Italian] The situation is absolutely under control.
‎（伊朗总统 2020年2月25日）
[in Persian] This is one of our enemies’ plots,
‎这是敌人的阴谋之一 ‎想把我们的国家拖入瘫痪
dragging the country to a shutdown.
‎我们应当一切照常
[in English] We should be going about our business as usual.
‎（巴西总统 2020年3月10日）
[in Portuguese] A lot of that is fantasy when it comes to the coronavirus.
‎谈到冠状病毒时 很多都是想象
‎没人想到会有如此大规模的流行病
[in English] Nobody knew there'd be a pandemic
or an epidemic of this proportion.
‎但许多从事传染病研究的人都知道 ‎流行病爆发即将来临
[narrator] But many who work in infectious disease
knew a pandemic like this was coming.
‎事实上 在2019年的春天
In fact, in the spring of 2019,
‎出现第一例COVID-19病例的几个月前
months before the first case of COVID-19,
‎我们为了节目  采访过这些人
we interviewed several of them for this show.
‎如果要想象一种情况
Well, if you think of anything that could come along
‎能够导致数百万人死亡
that would kill millions of people,
‎流行病是风险最高的
the pandemic is our greatest risk.
‎就死亡人数而言
In terms of the death toll,
‎流行病甚至可以 ‎与昔日的大规模战争相提并论
a pandemic would rival even the gigantic wars of the past.
‎经济将会停滞 ‎人类将会付出难以想象的代价
The economy will shut down, the cost to humanity will be unbelievable,
‎由此带来的问题 ‎没有一个国家能幸免
and no country will be immune from the problem this will create.
‎确实需要非凡的政治意愿 才能去说
[Maryn McKenna] It really takes an extraordinary act of political will
‎“是的 现在事情看起来没有那么糟糕
to say, "Yes, right now, things don't look that bad,
‎但无论如何 ‎我们都要向公共卫生提供资金
but we're going to send funding to public health anyway,
‎因为我们知道总有一天
because we know that someday it will be bad."
‎它会变糟的”
‎我们估计野生动物中 ‎大约有150万种病毒
We estimate there are around 1.5 million viruses in wildlife
‎都是我们还不了解的
that we don't yet know about.
‎其中任何一种 ‎都有可能扩散到人类之中
Any one of those could be spilling over into human population right now.
‎当一种病毒从动物传染给人类时 ‎它被称为人畜共患病毒
[narrator] When a virus jumps from an animal to a human,
it's called a zoonotic virus,
‎几十年来
and for decades,
‎这些新型病毒引起了越来越多的疫情
these kinds of new viruses have been causing more and more outbreaks.
‎我们知晓一些非常致命的病毒
We know some pretty lethal ones,
‎但我们预计还有其他更致命的病毒
but we expect that there are others out there that are more lethal,
‎更容易传播
that are better at being transmitted,
‎我们没有药物和疫苗 ‎这是最大的风险
where we've got no drugs and no vaccines. They're the big risk.
‎2002年的SARS就是这种情况
[narrator] That's what happened with SARS in 2002,
‎这是一种新型冠状病毒 ‎在全世界传播 导致数百人死亡
which was a new coronavirus that spread around the world, killing hundreds.
‎2012年 中东呼吸综合症再次爆发
And it happened again with MERS in 2012,
which was also a new coronavirus that killed hundreds.
‎这也是一种新型冠状病毒 ‎导致数百人死亡
‎这些疫情在全世界范围内
These outbreaks caused panic around the world,
‎引起短暂恐慌
for a brief moment.
‎但是专家们依旧非常担忧
But experts, they stayed worried.
‎像SARS或MERS这样的风险
There's a risk with something like SARS or MERS,
‎是我们还没有准备好应对的
that it'll be something we're not ready for.
‎会再次爆发冠状病毒吗？肯定的
Could it be a coronavirus again? Certainly.
‎当然 事实也确实如此
[narrator] And of course, it was.
[indistinct talking]
[patient coughing]
‎那么 在所有病毒中
[narrator] So, of all the viruses out there, why did this one
‎为什么这次会变成一次大流行呢？
end up becoming the kind of pandemic we haven't seen in more than a century?
‎已经一个多世纪没有发生过了
‎像这样的流行病是如何结束的呢？
And how does a pandemic like this end?
‎病毒跟炸弹或导弹一样具有毁灭性
[man] A virus can be just as destructive as a bomb or a missile.
[sneezes]
‎我们深感忧虑
[Tedros Ghebreyesus] We're deeply concerned
‎病毒传播速度 ‎以及不作为的情况十分惊人
by the alarming levels of spread and inaction.
‎COVID-19是一种流行病
COVID-19 is a pandemic.
‎全球病例继续增加
[Anthony Fauci] The cases continue to increase globally.
‎我们要做的 就是让疫情放缓
What we need to do is flatten that down.
‎发展中国家将会爆发疫情
[Daszak] We're going to have outbreaks in developing countries
‎而且会越来越严重
that are just going to be raging.
‎只有公众合作 ‎抗击传染病的运动才能取得成功
[man] The campaign against infectious disease can succeed
only if the public cooperates.
‎剧名：这场全球大流行病
‎病毒是地球上最早的生物之一…
[narrator] Viruses were one of the first living things on Earth...
‎但它们的生存机制跟我们不同
but they're not alive like we are.
‎它们需要劫持其他活细胞来繁殖
They need to hijack other living cells to reproduce,
‎这是它们唯一的目标
and that's their only goal,
‎生存和自我复制
to survive and replicate themselves.
‎这种病毒的官方名称是SARS-CoV-2
The official name of this virus is SARS-CoV-2.
‎"COVID-19"是其引起的疾病的名字
"COVID-19" is the name of the disease it causes,
‎意指“2019年冠状病毒疾病”
which stands for "Coronavirus disease 2019."
‎冠状是“王冠”的意思
Corona, as in "crown."
‎这种病毒以其冠状突起而得名
The virus is named for its crown-like spikes.
‎当我们打喷嚏、咳嗽或说话时 ‎它通过飞沫传播
It spreads through droplets when we sneeze, cough, or speak,
‎可以通过我们的眼睛、鼻子或嘴巴 ‎直接进入我们体内
and can enter us directly through our eyes, nose, or mouth.
‎病毒也可以在很多表面存活数小时
The virus can also live on a lot of surfaces for hours,
‎所以人们会用手沾上病毒
so people can pick it up on their hands
‎如果触摸自己的脸 就会感染自己
and infect themselves if they touch their face,
‎一般人每小时会摸脸20次
something the average person does 20 times an hour.
‎一旦进入体内 ‎这些突起就像一把钥匙
Once inside the body, those spikes act as a key,
‎锁定在许多人类细胞外部的蛋白质上
locking onto the proteins found on the outside of many human cells.
‎一旦病毒侵入
Once it's broken in,
‎它就会给细胞指令 ‎让细胞复制更多的自己
the virus gives the cell instructions to produce more copies of itself,
‎进而侵入越来越多的细胞
potentially invading more and more cells,
‎导致发烧、咳嗽和乏力
which can lead to a fever, a cough, and fatigue,
‎但也不总是如此
but not always.
‎也可能导致这些症状
And it potentially leads to any of these symptoms, too.
‎研究还在进行之中
Research is ongoing.
‎你可能感染并传播 而没有任何症状
And you can be infected and spread it without any symptoms,
‎或者可能被误认为是流感
or they can be mistaken for the flu.
‎这就是这种冠状病毒如此狡猾的原因
That's what makes this coronavirus so devious.
‎引发重大疾病的病毒 ‎通常具有如下特点
So the most significant diseases are often caused by viruses that
‎症状不明显 病程缓慢 ‎例如艾滋病毒
are silent and slow, like HIV,
‎或者发病很快 引起咳嗽、发烧等
or move very rapidly and cause symptoms like coughing and fever
‎可能与其他疾病混淆的症状
that could be confused with other diseases.
‎在日常生活中 一个冠状病毒携带者
[narrator] Going about their life, a person with this coronavirus
‎可能会感染几个人
likely infects a couple other people,
‎每个被感染者又会感染几个人
and each of those people infects a couple more,
‎如此反复
and so on, and so on,
‎所以病例数才会呈指数曲线增长
which is why the number of cases increases on an exponential curve,
‎每过几天 数量就会翻倍
doubling every several days.
‎其中一些人会患上严重的肺部感染
Then some of those people will end up with a severe lung infection,
and certain groups are especially at risk.
‎某些群体的风险尤其高
‎在美国一项样本中 ‎约四分之三的住院患者
In one US sample, around three-quarters of people who were hospitalized
‎至少有一种基础疾病
had at least one underlying health condition,
‎比如肺病、心脏病或糖尿病
like lung disease, heart disease, or diabetes.
‎虽然具体数字因国家而异
And while the exact numbers vary by country,
‎但随着年龄增长 死亡风险明显增加
the risk of dying is clearly greater the older you get,
‎如同这组数据所示 ‎这是疫情爆发两个月后
as you can see in this data that Hubei, China reported
‎中国湖北报告的数据
two months after their outbreak began.
‎由于科学家们还不完全了解的原因
And for reasons scientists don't fully understand,
‎男性感染的风险更高
the risk is also higher for men,
‎可能是由于一些生理因素
possibly because of some biological factors,
‎或者因为男性吸烟人数更多
or because they're more likely to smoke,
‎还有一种原因 一些研究表明
or because men, according to some studies,
‎男性更不喜欢洗手
aren't as good about washing their hands.
‎说到这里…
On that note...
‎尽可能勤洗手
Wash your hands as often as you possibly can,
‎我知道大家不是总能方便做到洗手
and I know you're not always in a position to be able to wash your hands,
‎但还是要尽量勤洗手
uh, but wash them as much as you can.
‎这是很好的建议
[narrator] It's good advice.
‎这种冠状病毒 ‎是已知感染人类的七种冠状病毒中
Now, this coronavirus is just the youngest in a whole family of seven coronaviruses
‎最年轻的一种
known to infect humans.
‎它现在像SARS和MERS一样出名了
It's now famous, as are SARS and MERS,
‎因为已经导致很多人死亡
because they've killed a lot of people.
‎但这四种病毒 ‎其实是更成功的病毒
But these four are actually more successful viruses.
‎三分之一的普通感冒都是它们引起的
They cause up to a third of common colds.
‎它们无处不在
They're everywhere.
‎因为如果病毒不会导致宿主生病
Because viruses can actually be better at spreading
‎那么传播会更加容易
if they don't make their host that sick.
‎可以看看蝙蝠
Just look at bats.
‎蝙蝠身上满是病毒 ‎因为病毒并不会影响它们
They're teeming with viruses because viruses don't really bother them.
‎但是…
But...
‎一旦进入人群 ‎就会变异成一种新的病毒
They can transform into a new virus once they get into the human population.
‎科学家认为 2002年的SARS就是这样
[narrator] That's what scientists believe happened with SARS in 2002.
‎就像这种冠状病毒一样
Just like this coronavirus,
‎SARS也出现在中国的活畜市场
SARS emerged in a live animal market in China.
‎由于它是一种新的人畜共患病毒
And since it was a new zoonotic virus,
‎没有治疗方法 也没有疫苗
there were no treatments and no vaccine.
‎但相比新型冠状病毒 ‎SARS的危险性要小得多
But SARS was a lot less dangerous than this coronavirus.
‎只有在出现症状时 才会传播
People could only spread it when they had symptoms,
‎所以更容易控制病毒传播
so it was easier to contain the virus by just quarantining people who were sick.
‎只需隔离发病的患者即可
‎SARS的致死率也高得多
SARS was also a lot more deadly,
‎这也使得病毒更难传播
which made it harder for the virus to spread.
‎像SARS这样的疾病 致死率在10%
[Daszak] A disease like SARS, it kills 10% of people it infects,
‎幸存者可能会获得一些免疫力 ‎可以不再被感染
and then the survivors probably have some immunity and can't be reinfected.
‎最终 只有拥有免疫的人
And eventually, the only people the virus can find
‎才被发现携带病毒
are people who have immunity to it.
‎SARS最终感染了 ‎至少29个国家的大约8000人
[narrator] In the end, SARS infected around 8,000 people
in at least 29 countries.
‎其中774人死亡
Seven hundred seventy-four of them died.
‎从那时起 ‎一个名为生态健康联盟的组织
Since then, a group called EcoHealth Alliance
‎来到中国南方的这些洞穴
has been coming to these caves in southern China,
‎捕捉蝙蝠
catching bats,
‎检测它们的病毒
scanning them for viruses,
‎标记那些最容易感染人类的病毒
and flagging the ones that could most easily make the leap to us.
‎发现病毒以后 我们会启动警报
[Daszak] And when we find them, we raise the alert,
‎中国政府会参与进来
and the government of China comes in
‎努力减少人群对病毒的接触
and tries to reduce the exposure of those populations to viruses.
‎到目前为止 他们发现了很多病毒 ‎包括数百种冠状病毒
[narrator] They've found a lot so far, including hundreds of coronaviruses.
‎他们将其标记为高风险或低风险
And they label them as high risk or low risk,
‎标准是与已经感染人类的病毒 ‎相似程度有多高
depending on how similar they are to viruses that already infect humans.
‎几年前 他们发现了一种病毒
And a few years ago, they discovered one that they called
‎他们称之为“蝙蝠冠状病毒RaTG13”
"bat coronavirus RaTG13,"
‎符合低风险标准
which met the criteria for low-risk.
‎当科学家们对COVID-19的病毒基因组 ‎进行测序时
When scientists sequenced the genome of the virus behind COVID-19,
‎他们发现有96%与蝙蝠病毒相同
they found that 96% of it was identical to that bat virus.
‎科学家们认为 ‎可能是蝙蝠病毒进化成了这种新病毒
Scientists believe the bat virus likely evolved into this new virus
‎进而感染人类
that could infect humans.
‎所以我们回去找了达什亚克医生
So we had to go back to Dr. Daszak.
‎当时 我们的目标 ‎是发现与SARS相关的病毒
At the time, our goal was to find SARS-related viruses.
‎这种病毒看起来相差甚远
This one looked too distant.
‎我们认为它不会进入人群
We didn't think it would be able to get into people.
‎看起来不像是迫在眉睫的明确危险
It didn't look like it was a clear and present danger.
‎非常遗憾
Unfortunate.
‎想要预测病毒进化的所有方式 ‎是不可能的
[narrator] It's impossible to predict all the ways a virus might evolve.
‎科学家们认为 这种病毒 ‎可能在另一种蝙蝠身上发生了突变
Scientists believe this one may have mutated in another bat...
‎或者在感染人类前 ‎先感染了另一个物种
or it may have jumped to another species before jumping to us,
‎比如穿山甲或蛇…
like a pangolin or a snake...
‎或鱼
or a fish.
‎一个多世纪以前 ‎堪萨斯州的一个农场发生过类似意外
That same kind of fluke happened on a farm in Kansas over a century ago.
‎专家们并不确定
Experts aren't certain,
‎但他们认为 1918年的流感大流行
but they believe the 1918 flu pandemic could have started
‎可能是感染流感的鸟类 ‎跟感染流感的人类 接触过同一只猪
when a bird with the flu and a human with the flu met the same pig.
‎禽流感不会感染人类
The bird flu couldn't infect humans,
‎人类流感也不会感染禽类
and the human flu couldn't infect birds,
‎但在猪的细胞中 这两种病毒结合
but in one of the pig's cells, those two viruses combined,
‎产生了一种新型人畜共患病毒
creating a new zoonotic virus,
‎H1N1
H1N1,
‎这种新病毒肯定会感染人类
and that new virus definitely could infect humans.
‎这次历史事件是史无前例的
It was unlike anything else in history.
‎一种疾病想要成为流行病
[narrator] For a disease to become a pandemic,
‎在几个月内在全世界蔓延 ‎导致数百万人死亡
spreading around the world in months, leading to potentially millions of deaths,
‎它必须在传染性和致命性之间
it has to find an extraordinary balance...
‎找到一种完美平衡
of contagiousness and deadliness.
‎可以从这两个维度来考虑一种疾病
You can think of a disease on those two scales.
‎这些是一些传染病
And these are some of the infectious diseases
‎它们是人类最大的敌人
that have been humanity's greatest foes.
‎这是人类季节性流感
Here's the seasonal human flu,
‎这是禽流感
while this is the bird flu.
‎1918年的流感在这个范围的某个地方
And somewhere in this range was the 1918 combination.
‎病毒通过空气传播
It was airborne,
‎意味着这种病毒可以悬浮在空气中 ‎感染任何吸入的人
meaning the virus could hang in the air, infecting anyone who inhaled it.
‎据估计 全球有三分之一的人口 ‎感染了这种病毒
And it's estimated that it infected one in every three people on Earth,
‎导致3-20%的感染者死亡
and then it killed anywhere from three to 20% of those infected.
‎当时的医疗记录并不完备
Medical record-keeping was not great at that time.
‎但跟天花比起来 ‎这种病毒根本不算什么
But that was nothing compared to smallpox,
‎天花的致死率为30%
which killed 30% of the people who got it,
‎也更具传染性
and was also more contagious.
‎几千年间 天花病毒都令人类恐惧
That virus terrorized humanity for thousands of years.
‎仅在20世纪
In the 20th century alone,
‎就夺去了数亿人的生命
it killed hundreds of millions of people.
‎还有更致命的埃博拉病毒
And then there's Ebola, which is even deadlier.
‎但埃博拉的致死人数少很多
But far fewer people have died from it,
‎部分原因是因为致死率太高
in part because it's so deadly,
‎感染埃博拉病毒的人不会感染很多人 ‎因为他们病得很重
people who have it don't infect too many others because they get so sick,
‎只能留在家中
they stay home,
‎最终都走向死亡
and then most don't survive.
‎关于病毒 有一件令人意想不到的事
One of the unexpected things about viruses is that sometimes,
‎症状明显、致死率高的病毒
a virus that has really obvious symptoms, that kills people at a very high rate,
‎通常不会爆发 它做不到
doesn't become a pandemic. It can't do that.
‎而像麻疹这样的疾病 ‎其致死率远低于埃博拉病毒
[narrator] While a disease like measles, which is far less deadly than Ebola,
‎曾经每年导致数百万人死亡
used to kill millions of people a year.
‎那么 当前的流行病在什么位置呢？
So where does this current pandemic fall?
‎目前还不清楚
It's not clear yet,
‎但专家们把它放在了这块区域
but experts place it somewhere around here.
‎比麻疹更致命 但传染性更小
Deadlier than the measles, but less contagious.
‎远没有埃博拉致命
Far less deadly than Ebola,
‎也远没有天花那么糟糕
and nowhere near as bad as smallpox.
‎接近于对1918年流感的较低估计
It's close to the lower estimates for the 1918 flu.
‎所以情况可能会更糟
So, it could be worse.
‎但病毒的平衡性 ‎足以造成毁灭性的后果
But its balance is just bad enough to be devastating.
‎但这并不意味着我们注定要重蹈覆辙
But that doesn't mean we're doomed to repeat history.
‎我们可以终结流行病
We can end pandemics. We've done it before.
‎我们也曾做到过
‎在20世纪 我们发现了抗生素
In the 20th century, we discovered antibiotics.
‎所以黑死病等细菌性疾病的致死率 ‎大大降低了
So the Bubonic Plague and all these other bacterial diseases became far less deadly.
‎但抗生素对这种冠状病毒 ‎或任何病毒都无效
But antibiotics don't work against this coronavirus, or any viruses.
‎我们有针对其中一些疾病的有效药物 ‎比如艾滋病…
We have effective drugs for some of them, like HIV...
‎如今 传染性和致命性都大大降低了
which can now be far less contagious and deadly.
‎但安全的抗病毒药物的研发难度很高
But safe antiviral drugs are really hard to develop.
‎所以战胜病毒的最好方法 ‎就是通过免疫
So the best way to defeat a virus is through immunity.
‎当某些病毒在人群中传播时
When certain viruses spread through a population,
‎一些感染者死亡…
some infected people die...
‎另一些人得以幸存
but others survive.
‎他们的免疫系统 ‎学会了识别病毒并将其击退
Their immune systems have learned to recognize the virus and fight it off.
‎当足够多的人获得免疫时 ‎病毒就更难传播了
When that happens in enough people, it's much harder for the virus to spread.
‎这就是所谓的群体免疫
This is called herd immunity.
‎感染率会放缓
The rate of infection slows.
‎然后病毒就会消失了
[Daszak] And the virus dies out.
‎但对于COVID-19 ‎如果世界只是等待群体免疫的到来
[narrator] But with COVID-19,
if the world just waited to achieve herd immunity naturally,
‎那会导致数百万人死亡
millions would die,
‎而且其他冠状病毒 ‎甚至不会产生终身免疫
and other coronaviruses don't even give lifelong immunity.
‎对于新型冠状病毒 我们还不了解
For this one, we just don't know yet.
‎这使得研制疫苗变得更加重要
Which makes it even more crucial that we create a vaccine.
‎如果有足够多的人接种疫苗
If enough people get vaccinated,
‎就能够安全快捷地获得群体免疫
it's a safe and life-saving shortcut to herd immunity.
‎第一例疫苗是用来对付天花的
The first vaccine was created to fight smallpox.
‎1980年 ‎在大规模的全球疫苗接种运动之后
And in 1980, after a massive global vaccination campaign,
‎天花成为世界上 ‎第一个被宣布根除的病毒
smallpox was the first virus ever declared eradicated from the world.
‎这些疾病造成的死亡人数 ‎也明显低于过去了
And these diseases don't cause nearly the amount of deaths they used to.
‎但是疫苗也是很难研发的
But vaccines are also really hard to develop.
‎要用一年到一年半的时间 ‎才能知道它是否有效
It's gonna take a year to a year and a half to really know if it works.
‎在此期间 ‎病毒还在继续传播和致死
[narrator] And while we wait, the virus keeps spreading and killing.
‎所以我们能做的 就是减缓病毒传播
So the best we can do is slow it down,
using a method that's a lot more old school.
‎使用一种更加老式的方法
‎其实这种方法是在七个世纪前发明的
In fact, it was invented seven centuries ago
‎以应对黑死病
during the Black Death:
‎那就是隔离
quarantine.
‎或者稍微温和一些的方法 ‎“保持社交距离”
Or its gentler cousin, "social distancing":
‎避免聚集以及跟他人亲密接触
avoiding crowds and close contact with other people
‎让病毒传播的机会更少
so the virus has fewer chances to spread.
‎1918年流感期间 美国的一个城市
During the 1918 flu, one American city,
‎圣路易斯 很快采取了这种做法
St. Louis, took that approach quickly,
‎关闭了学校和公共场所
shutting its schools and public places,
‎而费城没有马上这样做
while Philadelphia didn't right away,
and allowed a big parade to go ahead.
‎依旧允许举行大型游行
‎这是圣路易斯的死亡率
This was the death rate in St. Louis.
‎这是费城的死亡率
And this was Philadelphia's.
‎圣路易斯做到了使疫情曲线平缓
St. Louis flattened their curve,
‎这意味着 ‎疾病会在较长一段时间内造成死亡
which means the disease killed people for a longer period,
‎但死亡人数更少
but fewer died.
‎因为正如意大利在三月份意识到的
Because, as Italy learned in March,
‎如果太多人同时感染
it's much harder for hospitals to save lives
‎医院的救治难度就很大
if too many people get infected at once.
[in Italian] I’m living in the hospital, literally.
‎我已经住在医院里了
‎（法比奥阿里戈尼医生）
[in Italian] I’m living in the hospital, literally.
‎我睡在办公室 住在这里
I sleep in the office and I live here.
‎如此大量的严重病患
[woman speaking Italian] Such concentrated and intense suffering.
‎是我这辈子都没见过的
I've never seen this much of it in my life.
‎人们情况很危重
[in English] People are critical.
‎到这种程度时 ‎你会发现自己的无力感
When you arrive at this point, you realize that you are not enough.
‎我们显然想避免这种情况
[narrator] We obviously want to avoid that,
‎所以许多世界领导人 ‎都发出了同样的呼吁
which is why many world leaders have made the same plea.
‎回家
Go home and stay home.
‎呆在家里
‎大家必须呆在家里
You must stay at home.
‎（印度总理 2020年3月22日）
[in Hindi] During this time,
‎在这段时间里 ‎任何印度公民都不应走出家门
no Indian citizen should step out of their home.
‎全世界数以亿计的人一直在等待…
[narrator in English] Hundreds of millions of people around the world
have been waiting this out...
‎寻找应对之策
finding ways to cope.
[banging on pots]
[music playing on speakers]
‎所以这些国家必须进行严格的封锁
So countries really have to go on a hardcore national lockdown
‎才能真正放缓疫情曲线
to really suppress that curve,
and then we have to, at some point,
‎然后 在某个时刻
‎我们必须慢慢地、小心地解除封锁
gradually and carefully come out of that lockdown.
‎韩国就是一个典型
[narrator] South Korea is one model. As of early April,
‎四月初
‎他们在没有封锁的情况下 ‎成功控制住了疫情
they've managed to rein in their outbreak without a lockdown
‎他们通过广泛检测和追踪 ‎检测阳性的人群
by testing widely and retracing the steps of people who came back positive.
‎其他地方如果想要做到这样
For other places to pull off something similar,
‎他们就需要加大检测力度
they'd need to ramp up their testing.
‎在疫情曲线的什么位置 ‎你会回去复工？
At what point on the other side of the curve do you go back to work?
‎没有答案 我觉得答案就是加强检测
There is no answer. I think the answer's gonna be in testing.
‎如果今天可以检测数百万人
If you could test, today, millions of people,
‎那明天就可以让他们复工 对吧？
you could send them to work tomorrow, right?
‎问题是如果我们不够小心
The problem is if we're not careful,
‎这种被抑制的爆发 ‎可能会持续很长一段时间
that smoldering outbreak can last a long time.
‎还记得圣路易斯吗？
[narrator] Remember St. Louis?
‎在这里 在11月份
Right there, in November,
‎城市决定终止保持社交距离的政策
is when the city decided to end their social distancing policies.
‎死亡率随后上升 城市很快又被封锁
The death rate jumped, and the city quickly locked down again.
‎对于这样的流行病
In a pandemic like this,
‎除非疫苗研制成功
until you have a vaccine,
‎否则选择十分有限
you have limited options,
‎因为病毒已经先发制人
because the virus had a head start.
‎这是专家们一直担心的情况
And this is a situation that experts have always feared.
‎大自然是终极的生物恐怖分子
Mother Nature is the ultimate bioterrorist.
‎总有一些事情会让我们惊讶
There are always going to be things that surprise us
‎让我们措手不及
and that take our detection by surprise.
‎我们可以对流感或SARS这样的流行病 ‎做好更充分的准备
[Gates] We could be far more ready for a pandemic like a flu or a SARS.
‎但如果出现快速传播的呼吸道病原体
However, if a really fast-moving respiratory pathogen came out,
‎我们将无法控制数字增长
no, we wouldn't be able to hold those numbers down.
‎世界卫生组织的使命是领导全球
[narrator] The World Health Organization is meant to lead the global response
‎应对这样的流行病
to a pandemic like this.
‎但其实世卫组织是一个很小的组织
But it's actually quite a small organization,
‎极度依赖自愿捐款
very dependent on voluntary contributions.
‎所以他们没有飞机或团队随时待命
So they don't have planes or teams standing by.
‎他们没有研发预算
They don't have a research and development budget
‎来制造这些工具
to make these tools.
‎2005年 世界卫生组织 ‎描绘了一幅巨大的蓝图
[narrator] In 2005, the WHO did draw up a huge blueprint
‎告诉世界如何准备和应对这样的危机
for how the world should prepare and respond to a crisis like this.
‎其中强调
Among other things,
‎各国必须完善发现疫情的能力
countries had to develop the capacity to detect outbreaks
‎并迅速报告世界卫生组织
and quickly notify WHO.
‎196个国家签署了这份协议
One hundred and ninety-six countries signed onto this,
‎但大多数国家从未遵守
but most never complied.
‎无论何种规模的流行病爆发
When a pandemic comes along of any size,
‎我们总是追悔莫及 ‎希望曾经投入了更多资金
we always look back and wish we'd invested more.
‎然而 我们的记忆很快就会淡忘
However, very quickly our memory fades,
‎其他事项就会优先获得资源
and other priorities are getting the resources.
‎世卫组织最近的一份报告甚至承认
[narrator] A recent WHO report even acknowledged,
‎“呼吸道病原体的迅速蔓延
"There is a very real threat
‎以及严重致命性 ‎是一种非常现实的威胁
of a rapidly moving, highly lethal pandemic of a respiratory pathogen.
‎全球尚未做好准备”
The world is not prepared."
‎那是第一例COVID-19病例 ‎发生的三个月前
That was three months before the first case of COVID-19.
‎我们的医疗体系显然没有做好准备
And our healthcare systems obviously weren't prepared.
‎世界各地的医生和护士 ‎被迫使用未达标准的口罩
Doctors and nurses around the world have been forced to use makeshift masks.
‎过去两天里 有八名护士病倒了
[in Spanish] In the last two days, eight nurses have fallen ill.
‎医护人员都生病了
[in English] Healthcare professionals are sick.
‎我们需要先得到保护 ‎才能提供治疗
We need to be protected first so that we'll be able to help.
‎在中国 第一批感染COVID-19的人
[narrator] And in China, many of the first people with COVID-19
‎很多都是在医院里感染的
appear to have caught the disease at a hospital.
‎全世界花了很多钱来准备战争
Well, the world spends a lot of money preparing for war.
‎军事预算很高
Military budgets are large, and the new weapons get created.
‎新型武器不断研制
‎这也是属于战争的
This belongs right there with war,
‎我们理应做好应对
as something that we plan for.
‎我们还需要在第一时间
[narrator] We also need to do more  to prevent outbreaks
‎采取更多措施 防止疫情的发生
from happening in the first place.
‎像这样的活畜市场
Live animal markets like this
‎在中国和其他国家的部分地区 ‎仍然很受欢迎
have remained popular in parts of China and other countries,
‎使动物病毒有各种机会混合变异
giving animal viruses all kinds of opportunities to mix and mutate
‎并传染给人类
and jump to humans.
‎当疫情爆发时 ‎我们需要更快地做出反应
And when there is an outbreak, we need to respond faster.
‎在中国开始 ‎对COVID-19采取管控措施的三周前
Three weeks before China began any containment measures against COVID-19...
‎33岁的武汉中心医院医生
a 33-year-old doctor at Wuhan Central Hospital,
‎李文亮医生
Doctor Li Wenliang,
‎给其他医生发了一条群聊
sent a group chat to other doctors,
‎提醒他们注意疫情爆发
alerting them to the outbreak.
‎几天后 ‎武汉警方令其在训诫书上签字
A few days later, the Wuhan police made him sign a letter,
‎警告说他将受到法律的制裁
warning that he would receive the full sanction of the law
‎如果他继续“固执己见”
if he "stubbornly persists" in his opinions.
‎1月30日 世界卫生组织 ‎宣布进入公共卫生紧急状态时
By the time the WHO declared a public health emergency on January 30th,
‎李文亮医生可能已经感染COVID-19…
Dr. Li Wenliang had likely already contracted COVID-19...
‎因为他在一周后病逝
because he died of it a week later.
‎三周后
And three weeks after that,
‎据估计 中国有11.4万人被感染
it's estimated that 114,000 people in China were infected.
‎如果中国在一周前就实施了管控措施
If China had implemented its containment measures just one week earlier,
‎研究发现 感染人数会是这样的
researchers found it would have looked like this.
‎（受感染城市）
‎提前两周 会是这样
Two weeks earlier, like this.
‎提前三周
And three weeks earlier,
‎会是这样
like this.
‎病例数本可以减少95%的
The number of cases could have been cut by as much as 95%.
‎虽然中国在二月份已经进入封锁
And while China was locked down in February,
‎意大利并非如此
Italy wasn't,
‎结果成为病毒爆发的第二个中心
and it became the next epicenter of the virus.
‎当意大利在三月进入封锁时
And when Italy locked down in March,
‎美国并没有采取措施
the United States didn't,
‎于是沦为第三个中心
and became the next epicenter.
‎然后在更加贫穷的国家 ‎病例数开始上升 那里的封锁更困难
And then cases started to rise  in poorer countries
where lockdowns are harder,
‎医疗系统本就非常脆弱
and healthcare systems, already fragile.
‎我们需要加快封锁的速度
We need to get faster at containment.
‎理想情况下 ‎我们希望从源头上捕获更多病毒
Ideally, we want to catch more viruses at the source.
‎不仅是在中国
It isn't just China,
‎不仅针对蝙蝠
and it isn't just bats.
‎这些地方是 ‎新型病毒最有可能传播给人类的地方
These are the places where a new virus is most likely to make the leap to humans.
‎疾病首先出现在这样的地方
The frontline for disease emergence are places like
‎比如热带森林的道路尽头
the end of the road in a tropical forest
‎有人刚刚拿到采矿特许权
where someone's just built a new mining concession.
‎人们搬进来
People have moved in,
‎没有食物供应 ‎所以他们出去捕猎野生动物
there's no food supply, so they go out and hunt wildlife.
‎或者是东南亚一个一直在扩张的农场
Or it's a farm in Southeast Asia that's been expanding and intensifying,
‎附近有蝙蝠 把病毒传给农场里的猪
that has bats nearby that spread viruses into the pigs in the farm.
‎事实是 世界各地的人类行为
[narrator] The truth is, human behavior all over the world
‎使得像这样的流行病不可避免
has made pandemics like this one inevitable.
‎砍伐森林使更多的野生动物 ‎与更多人类接触
Deforestation is bringing more wild animals into contact with more people,
and factory farming is pushing animals closer together,
‎工厂化养殖使动物们的距离更近
‎使病毒有更多的机会融合 ‎进而感染人类
giving their viruses more opportunities to combine into one that could infect us.
‎我们给了它们更多的传播途径
Then we give them more ways than ever to spread.
‎我觉得 流行病的一个重要教训是
[Daszak] I think one of the big lessons about pandemics is,
‎我们总认为流行病是在别处爆发的
we think that it's something happening over there.
‎从COVID-19可以看出
Well, we know from COVID-19
‎别处爆发的流行病 很容易传到身边
that what happens over there can very easily get here.
‎但是如果病毒能够思考
[narrator] But if viruses were capable of thinking,
‎它们应该也会吸取教训
they should have also learned their lesson.
‎如果它们的目标是复制
If their goal is to replicate,
‎那它们就不应该害死我们
they shouldn't start killing us.
‎因为一旦病毒成为流行病
Because once a virus becomes a pandemic,
‎人类将会发挥所有聪明才智 ‎去摧毁它们
all of human ingenuity will be brought to bear to bring them down.
‎我们应当准备更加充分的
We should have been more prepared,
‎但说到技术、科学和协作
but when it comes to technology, science, and coordination,
‎我们的准备程度 已经高于以往
we've also never been more prepared.
‎这种新型病毒 ‎在几天内就被识别出来了
This new virus was identified within days. The sequence was shared a few days later,
‎几天后 基因序列就被分享了
‎正因为如此 才能开始检测
and because of that, testing began,
‎在全球范围内进行检测
really, across the globe.
‎世界各地的科学家正致力于研制疫苗
Scientists around the world are committing entire labs to creating a vaccine.
‎这是世界历史上
The... the fastest vaccine ever created, um, in history.
‎研制速度最快的疫苗
‎全球最快的超级计算机 ‎已经进行了上千次的模拟
[reporter] The world's fastest supercomputer
has run thousands of simulations
‎确定了77种 ‎可能有效阻止病毒的药物成分
and identified 77 drug compounds that might effectively stop the virus.
‎科学界这样聚集在一起 真是惊人
It's amazing the way the scientific community has gathered together.
‎我们知道代价如何
[narrator] We know what it takes,
‎因为自从地球有生命以来 ‎我们一直在和病毒赛跑
because we've been in this race since life on Earth began,
‎还没有一种病毒能够打败我们
and a virus hasn't beaten us yet.
[inaudible]
[banging on pots]
[music playing on speakers]
[theme music playing]